Guide to the Arthur Lazarus Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Arthur Lazarus papers
1947-2011
WA MSS S-2684
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
9.38
(23 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, notes, newspaper clippings and printed briefs relating to Arthur Lazarus, his activism in the area of Native American civil rights, and his legal clients. The papers document Lazarus's legal work for two prominent cases: Tuscarora Indian Nation v. Power Authority of the State of New York, which came before the Supreme Court in 1958, and Montana v. Blackfeet Tribe, which came before the Supreme Court in 1985. Other clients and cases are also documented in the briefs, correspondence and clippings.
Lazarus, Arthur
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Arthur Lazarus (Yale Law 1949), 1997, 2013.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arthur Lazarus Jr., 1926-
Arthur Lazarus is an attorney who specializes in American Indian Law. After graduating from Yale Law School in 1949, he worked with Felix Cohen in Washington D.C. until Cohen's death in 1953. Lazarus represented American Indian tribes in their claims against State and Federal governments, including several claims before the federal Indian Claims Commission. His clients included the Blackfeet Tribe, the Menominee Tribe, the Papago Tribe, the Seneca Nation, the Sioux Nation, and the Tuscarora Nation.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Business Papers,1951-1987. II. Legal Briefs, 1947-1996. III. September 2013 Acquisition.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, notes, newspaper clippings and printed briefs relating to Arthur Lazarus, his activism in the area of Native American civil rights, and his legal clients. The papers document Lazarus' legal work for two prominent cases: Tuscarora Indian Nation v. Power Authority of the State of New York, which came before the Supreme Court in 1958, and Montana v. Blackfeet Tribe, which came before the Supreme Court in 1985. Other clients and cases are also documented in the briefs, correspondence and clippings.
Indians of North America -- Government relations; Indians of North America -- Civil rights -- Montana; Indians of North America -- Civil rights -- New York (State); Indians of North America -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- Montana; Indians of North America -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- New York (State); Lawyers -- Washington (D.C.); Siksika Indians -- Legal status, laws, etc.; Siksika Indians -- Law and legislation; Tuscarora Indians -- Legal status, laws, etc.; Tuscarora Indians -- Law and legislation; Legal documents; Lawyers -- Washington (D.C.); Lazarus, Arthur; United States ( ICRA); United States. Indian Claims Commission
- Business papers, 1951-1987; Series I; 2.09; (5 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized roughly by topic.
  Scope and Contents
  Business Papers consist chiefly of retained carbons of outgoing correspondence to clients and associates and newspaper clippings, documenting in particular Lazarus's work with three tribes: the Tuscarora Nation, the Blackfeet Tribe, and the Seneca Nation. Lazarus's work with other clients and cases is also documented in the correspondence and clippings.
  - Correspondence, non-client, incoming and outgoing, 1952-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Tuscarora, 1957-1967 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - Blackfeet I, 1951-1957 (Box 2, Folder 6-8)
  - Blackfeet II, 1957-1963 (Box 2, Folder 9-11)
  - Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act land seminar, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
  - Articles by Felix Cohen, typescripts, printed versions, and related correspondence, 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Briefs, typescripts and file copies, 1954-1967 (Box 3, Folder 15-17)
  - Newspaper clippings relating to American Indian law, 1955-1958 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - American Civil Liberties Union, Indian Civil Rights Committee, minutes and correspondence, 1957-1961 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Newspaper clippings relating to the Tuscarora Nation, 1958-1960 (Box 4, Folder 20-24)
  - Newspaper clippings relating to the Tuscarora Nation (continued), 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Newspaper clippings relating to the Seneca Nation and Kinzua Dam, 1965-1976 (Box 5, Folder 26-29)
- Legal briefs, 1947-1996; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  Not arranged in any particular order.
  Legal briefs consist of printed versions of briefs authored by Arthur Lazarus and his associates, including Felix Cohen.
  - Legal briefs, 1947-1996 (Box 6, Folder 30-36)
- September 2013 acquisition, 1950-2011; 3; 6.88; (17 boxes)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of Arthur Lazarus (Yale Law 1949), 2013.
  This addition consists of correspondence, writings, printed material and legal papers, including legal briefs, documenting the legal work of Arthur Lazarus for Native American communities.
  Arranged roughly in the order in which it was received.
  - Memorandum AAIA, 1950-1953 (Box 7)
  - Memoranda (A. L., Jr. - Personal) AAIA, 1954 (Box 7)
  - A.L., Jr. AAIA, 1955-1956 (Box 7)
  - AAIA, 1957-1958 (Box 8)
  - Memoranda (A.L., Jr.) AAIA, 1959-1960 (Box 8)
  - AAIA - F.B.A. Convention - Chicago, 1960-09-17 (Box 8)
  - Legal papers, 1998-2003; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Legal papers, writings, and correspondence, 1979-1981 (Box 9)
  - "Filing: 1979/80 Yale Teaching File", 1979-1981 (Box 9)
  - Yale seminar materials, 1973 (Box 10)
  - "Yale - Indian Law Seminar- Fall 1975 lectures" (Box 10)
  - "Arthur Lazarus, Jr. - Seminar (Yale - Fall, 1973)" (Box 10)
  - AL, Jr. - Yale Law School, Indian Law seminar, 1977 (Box 10)
  - Yale Law School - materials, 1969-1976 (Box 10)
  - Printed legal material, 1952-2004; 4 folders (Box 11)
  - Tuscarora Post correspondence, 1971-1973 (Box 12)
  - AL, Jr. - Laguna correspondence, 1956-1973 (Box 12)
  - Navajo correspondence, 1971-1973 (Box 12)
  - AL, Jr. - Hualapai correspondence and legal papers, 1952-1973 (Box 12)
  - AL, Jr. - Nez Perce correspondence and legal papers, 1960-1973 (Box 13)
  - AL, Jr. - Metlakatla, 1970-1972 (Box 13)
  - AL, Jr. - Oglala Sioux correspondence, 1954-1973 (Box 13)
  - AL, Jr. - Salt River Pima-Maricopa correspondence, 1955-1973 (Box 13)
  - Doyon correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 13)
  - Legal papers, 1998-1999 (Box 14)
  - Legal correspondence, 1961-1965 (Box 14)
  - AL, Jr. - AAIA (1968 missing), 1966-1970 (Box 15)
  - Legistative memoranda - (A.L., Jr.) AAIA, 1958 (Box 16)
  - Legistative memoranda - (A.L., Jr.) AAIA, 1959 (Box 16)
  - Printed legal material, 1971-1997; 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Title II of the 1968 Civil Rights Act: an Indian Bill of Rights, undated (Box 17)
  - Legal material, 1980-2007; 4 folders (Box 17)
  - Legal material, 1999-2010; 4 folders (Box 18)
  - Legal material, 2008-2011; 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Correspondence, 1969-1971 (Box 20)
  - Legal papers and correspondence, 1998-2000 (Box 20)
  - Legal papers, 1999-2001; 4 folders (Box 20)
  - AL, Jr. - San Carlos Apache correspondence, 1953-1972 (Box 21)
  - AL, Jr. - Memos and correspondence, 1953-1999 (Box 22)
  - Blackfeet - McKat, Iliff (personal), 1953-1997 (Box 22)
  - "Miscellaneous Letters / Memos", 1968-1978 (Box 22)
  - Mississippi Sioux, correspondence, 1971-1973 (Box 23)
  - AL, Jr. - AAIA 1/1/70, 1971-1973 (Box 23)